<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Innocency no shield against envy A sermon preached on Friday, April 11. being the fast-day appointed by the Kings proclamation to seek reconciliation with God, &amp;c. By George Topham, rector of Boston in Lincolnshire. Perused and approved of by the right Reverend father in God, Thomas, Lord Bishop of Lincoln.</title>
            <author>Topham, George, d. 1694.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62951</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1906</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220703</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832095</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832095</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36564</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62951)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36564)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2100:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Innocency no shield against envy A sermon preached on Friday, April 11. being the fast-day appointed by the Kings proclamation to seek reconciliation with God, &amp;c. By George Topham, rector of Boston in Lincolnshire. Perused and approved of by the right Reverend father in God, Thomas, Lord Bishop of Lincoln.</title>
                  <author>Topham, George, d. 1694.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 36, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Thomas Fox, and are to be sold at his shop at the Angel in Westminster-Hall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a final advertisement leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms LIX, 3 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36564:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Innocency no Shield againſt Envy.</hi> A SERMON Preached on <hi>Friday, April</hi> 11. Being The Faſt-Day Appointed by the KINGS Proclamation To ſeek Reconciliation with God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> BY <hi>GEORGE TOPHAM,</hi> Rector of <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>Lincolnſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="imprimatur">
               <body>
                  <p>Peruſed and approved of by the Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>THOMAS,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Fox,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall.</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:36564:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36564:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached upon PSALM lix. 3. <hi>For lo, they lie waiting for my Soul: The mighty men are gathered againſt me without any offence or fault of me, O Lord.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat the Argument of this Pſalm is; why, when, and by whom written, the Title ſhews and tells us, that it was <hi>Davids,</hi> made when <hi>Saul</hi> ſent, and they watcht the houſe to kill him. I ſhall not trouble your atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the myſtical or Prophetical ſenſe of it, either as it relates to Chriſt or his Church; a diſcourſe more proper for ſome other ſeaſon; but only with the Hiſtorical or Literal, as it concerned King <hi>David,</hi> and by his example all that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed him in the like dangers and deliverances; and at this time fit for our more than ordinary Conſideration: For it is a Pſalm in which <hi>Iſraels</hi> ſweet Singer, makes his Addreſs to his God, by way of vindicating his own Innocency.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:36564:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>For lo, they lie waiting for my Soul: The mighty men are gathered againſt me without any offence or fault of me, O Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein be pleaſed to obſerve theſe particulars:</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Davids</hi> Petition, ver. 2. <hi>Deliver me from mine Enemies, O my God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, A deſcription of them,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By their practices, <hi>they lie waiting for my Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Of their perſons, <hi>the mighty men are gathered againſt me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, His Juſtification, <hi>Without any offence or fault of me, O Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, Upon his being delivered, his reſolution to praiſe God, ver. 16, 17. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto thee, O my ſtrength, will I ſing: for thou, O God, art my refuge, and my merciful God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of theſe in order.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Davids</hi> Petition, <hi>Deliver me, O my God.</hi> And ſurely never did greater reaſon and encouragement cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in any one perſon, more than in this Princely Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet: Nor ever had any man better aſſurance of the Almighties favour than himſelf; ſo that well may he ſtile him, not only God, but his God. How had he raiſed him from a low eſtate, to ſit upon no leſs than the Throne of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> changing his Shepherds Cap into a Crown, his Coat into a Robe, and his Staff into a Scepter? How had he given him, not only Courage to encounter, but Power to Conquer, that daring Philiſtim, whoſe very Bravadoes frighted the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> out of their Valour, and at once made them forget both God and themſelves? How oft had he turned his enemies Swords into their own breaſts, and maugre all their malice, chained Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory to his Conquering Chariot? Which made the Damoſels of <hi>Iſrael</hi> at his Triumphant return, playing ſing, and ſinging play, <hi>Saul hath ſlain his thouſands, but David his ten thouſands.</hi> It were endleſs by retail to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36564:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>reckon all the donatives that Heaven beſtowed upon this Prince: To the no leſs joy of himſelf, than the Envy and wonder of his Adverſaries. Yet the greateſt won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is, How <hi>David</hi> (a King and Saint, both which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title him to a more than ordinary intereſt in Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, for Kings are his Viceroys, and Saints his Friends, and <hi>David</hi> eminent in both relations) ſhould have ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and rebels.</p>
            <p>But if we rightly conſider, it will appear none, ſince no ſtate or condition of men upon earth is ſo expoſed to dangers as theirs: For it is one, and not one of the leaſt, unhappineſſes of the Sons of <hi>Adam;</hi> to be by nature proud and impatient of reſtraint, greedy of liberty, always diſſatisfied with the preſent, and thirſting after Novelties; ſcarce any content with their ſtation. Some are aſpiring, and would be higher; others covetous, and would be richer; ſome revengeful, and will be quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling; ſome malicious, ſome turbulent, and many the like. Now all this croud of inordinate paſſions diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chargeth it ſelf upon thoſe in power and place, hoping by ſome publick diſturbance, that in troubled waters they may catch that which calmer times would have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon perſons of better merit.</p>
            <p>And the State, the Employ, the Condition of Kings, gives ſome advantage to ſuch intendments, for they ſtand high, all eyes are upon them, nothing they ſay or do eſcapes obſervation and cenſure. If any thing be amiſs (as in multiplicity of affairs it is impoſſible but there ſhould) they are ſure to hear of it, with all its hightning circumſtances; the giddy multitude not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that there may be a great Sacriledge committed in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and yet <hi>Joſhua</hi> not know of it: Some errors will eſcape the beſt vigilancy; that ſin is not half cunning enough that hath not learned ſecreſie, yet when ſuch miſcarriages happen, Magiſtracy muſt be traduced for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36564:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>it. Nay, how oft is their very innocency charged with aberrations? Making good holy <hi>Davids</hi> aſſertion, <hi>For lo, they lie waiting for my Soul, The mighty men are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered againſt me without any offence or fault of me, O Lord.</hi> Where be pleaſed to take notice how he deſcribes his Enemies.</p>
            <p>Firſt, By their policy, lying in wait for his Soul: that is, for his life. And how and when they did this, is ſet down, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> xix. 11. when <hi>Sauls</hi> unbounded malice miſt of its deſign, by <hi>Davids</hi> avoiding his darted Jave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin; his hatred purſues him home: Sending Meſſengers thither, under the pretence of a viſit, to ſlay him, and to bid him a good Morning with the loſs of his life. And though this Stratagem failed of its deſired end as well as the other; <hi>Saul</hi> will not fail of a further contrivance for his ruine, and that of a moſt unpardonable nature: To cozen under the colour of Amity, is the moſt exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable villany. And there is no defence for that Piſtol that is charged with the Bullet of friendſhip; yet ſuch was this of <hi>Sauls; Be thou valiant and fight the Lords Battels, and I will give thee my eldeſt Daughter Merab to Wife; for he ſaid, my hand ſhall not be upon him,</hi> 2 Sam. xviii. 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> was now grown ſo popular that the King durſt not offer him perſonal violence; therefore he hires him into the jaws of death, by no leſs a price than his eldeſt Daughter. What a Saint, what a Friend was <hi>Saul?</hi> Yet he never intended more miſchief to <hi>David,</hi> nor more unfaithfulneſs to his God than in this offer, for, for all theſe fair flouriſhes, he hoped <hi>David</hi> would have fallen by the Sword of the <hi>Philiſtins,</hi> as appeared by the not performing of his promiſe, for <hi>Merab</hi> was not given to <hi>David,</hi> but to <hi>Adriel.</hi> And now the breaking of his word muſt certainly be a ſufficient oblation to his hatred. No, revenge knows no limits: He has one plot more,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36564:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>by which he does not doubt, but to bring <hi>David</hi> to his Grave, if he will but bring him an hundred Foreskins of the Philiſtins, he has another Daughter which ſhall be his Wife: And though the yonger, yet the more affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate, ſhe was as ſick of love as her Father was of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred toward him. <hi>Saul</hi> is glad of this, his Daughter could never do him better ſervice: If <hi>Davids</hi> valour (over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heated with the hopes of her Eſpouſal) do but make him periſh in this attempt. But all thoſe projects failing, and <hi>Sauls</hi> death enſuing; ſure nothing now can diſcompoſe his reſt, or raiſe a ſtorm upon the face of his ſerene Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
            <p>Yes, this rare and excellent Perſon, this gracious Prince, the very light of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as his Subjects ſtiled him, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> xxi. 17. was reſtleſs all his days; I cannot reckon his troubles becauſe he himſelf ſays they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable, <hi>Pſal.</hi> xl. 12. nor his enemies that hated him without a cauſe, and ſought to deſtroy him wrongfully, for they were mighty, <hi>Pſal.</hi> xxxviii. 19. The Grandees; the graveſt that ſate in the Gate, (the place of Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature,) <hi>Pſal.</hi> lxix. 12. were thoſe that conſpired his deſtruction. Which is the next conſiderable, <hi>The mighty men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Had it only been the Drunkards, the ſcum of the People, that had made Songs of him, he would either have reduced them to their obedience, by ſome pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment ſuitable to their Crime; or with a noble ſcorn or pity have paſt by their affronts: But for the mighty men to lie in wait for his life, muſt needs not only awaken his diligence, but his devotion too, that Heaven would be pleaſed to fortifie his Guards againſt their treacheries, who were daily contriving his ruine. And that after the moſt inſinuating ways imaginable; traducing that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment which God himſelf never found fault with, and at laſt took Arms againſt him: And to make up his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36564:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſorrows to the full, who ſhould head theſe Rebels but his dearly beloved <hi>Abſolom;</hi> who drew into conſpiracy with him, beſides the moſt of his Fathers Subjects, even his familiar Friend <hi>Achitophel,</hi> whoſe Counſel, whilſt good, was as an Oracle of God, but, when bad, might ſtand in competition with the Devil; as appeared by that he gave <hi>Abſolom,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam</hi> xvi. 21. for he fearing that <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom</hi> ſhould relent, and <hi>David</hi> remit, and ſo that breach be pieced, he adviſed him to ſecond his unnatural Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy with as unnatural Inceſt; not only to violate his Fathers Throne, but his Fathers Bed: And this Villany not to be acted in ſecreſie, the argument of Fear or Modeſty, but ſo that all <hi>Iſrael</hi> might be Witneſſes of the Sons ſin, and the Fathers ſhame. And that this treaſon may end in victory, he has another deſign ready; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction may be an advantage to <hi>David:</hi> Therefore he reſolves, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> xvii. 2. <hi>I will purſue him to night, and come upon him while he is weary.</hi> How pernicious, how deſtructive was this intendment? For beſides the weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and unreadineſs of <hi>Davids</hi> Army, the ſpirits of that holy King were low and daunted: And had not <hi>Huſhai,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> xvii. 14. put a ſtop to this piece of <hi>Aohitophels</hi> policy, <hi>Davids</hi> Army had been half vanquiſhed ere one blow had been given.</p>
            <p>Thus was this excellent King uſed, by an unworthy Maſter, an unnatural Son, and an ungrateful Subject: Nay, that the Cup of his affliction may not want, but run over, they will not ſuffer him to die in peace, for <hi>Adonijah,</hi> another of his darling Sons, obtrudes himſelf a Succeſſor upon him, endeavouring as it were to bury him alive. But I ſhall proceed from their Cruelty to his Innocency, the third thing propoſed, <hi>Davids</hi> Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Without any offence or fault of me, O Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that this was no Complement, but a real truth, is evident to any that conſults the Hiſtory of his life.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36564:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>For he was a Pious man, a great Souldier, and a gracious Prince; one in whom nothing was wanting to oblige a people to obedience and reſpect; <hi>A man after Gods own heart,</hi> 1 Sam. xiii. 14. propoſed as a Pattern to <hi>Solomon,</hi> with a promiſe to entail his Kingdom and bleſſings upon him and his Poſterity, if he would but walk in his ſteps, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> vii. 17, 18. His life was the Meaſure and Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard, by which ſucceeding Princes were to be judged, his vertues out-lived himſelf, and many Generations fared the better for him.</p>
            <p>Yet you ſee this incomparable Prince, this Favorite of Heaven, this glory of after-Ages was continually di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed in his own, by the Seditions and Rebellions of his Enemies: Which made him ſay, <hi>They are minded to do me ſome miſchief, ſo maliciouſly are they bent againſt me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſurely theſe Perſons of Honour had ſome juſt cauſe to lie in wait for <hi>David,</hi> perhaps he had degraded them, or taken away their Eſtates, or at leaſt his riſing Sun had darkned and cauſed theirs to ſet in a cloud of diſgrace. No, he was not guilty of any of theſe: For as God was wonderful in placing him on his Throne, ſo was he merciful even to the worſt of his Enemies. How did he pardon that railing <hi>Shimei,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> xvi. 7. when he curſed him, ſaying, <hi>Come out thou bloudy man, and thou man of Belial.</hi> What Tongue, but that of this wicked Rebel, durſt thus have ſlandered the Majeſty of a King? Every word was a lie: He calls him an Uſurper, a man of bloud, and that of <hi>Sauls</hi> Houſe; how falſe! God ſent for him out of the fields to be Anointed, How was he an Intruder? The man after Gods own heart, is branded for a man of <hi>Belial,</hi> and he that regretted for but the cutting off <hi>Sauls</hi> Garment, is reproached as a man of bloud.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:36564:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Indeed, for his Maſter, what reſpect did he pay him? Meeting his Envy with Love; yea, at that very time that he ſought his death: for <hi>Saul</hi> being weary with purſuing of him, ſeeks a repoſe in <hi>Davids</hi> Cave, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> xxiv. 3. where <hi>David</hi> takes him napping, and now his Souldiers adviſe him to carve his own revenge; and to encourage him to it, they alledge Gods promiſe and this advantage concurring. But he, like himſelf, gives way, neither to his own paſſion, nor their ſolicitation, but only makes this opportunity the trial of his Loyalty, and the means of his Peace. It had been as eaſie to have cut <hi>Sauls</hi> Throat as his Garment; but his Coat not his Perſon ſhall be the worſe: Nor that neither but for a monument of his Innocency. Did he not ſhed the bloud of that <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lekite,</hi> who did but ſay he had ſhed <hi>Sauls?</hi> How did he bewail the death of ſo bad a Maſter; wiſhing no dew might fall where that Royal bloud was poured out?</p>
            <p>And as for <hi>Abſolom</hi> and <hi>Achitophel,</hi> what humane power could have done more than <hi>David</hi> did, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dear and ſecure the Duty of the one, and the Loyalty of the other? With what love and affection had he treated <hi>Abſolom?</hi> And for <hi>Achitophel,</hi> he made him not only of his Privy Council, but the Grand Miniſter both of his ſtate and favour. And therefore when this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful Politician turned Traitor, how deeply did it wound the Royal breaſt that had advanced him? For it was not (ſays he, <hi>Pſal.</hi> lv. 12.) an enemy that reproached me, then I could have born it; neither was it he that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me, that did magnifie himſelf againſt me, then I would have hid my ſelf from him: But it was thou, a man, mine equal, my guide, and mine acquaintance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> thou whom I had honoured, thou whom I had preferred, thou whoſe growing greatneſs knew no Rivality.</p>
            <p>But <hi>David</hi> had his faults, and great ones too, for which he was puniſhed! It is true, he had ſo, but none
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36564:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>to provoke his People to diſobedience, they were private and perſonal, not of publick Concernment, his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was juſt and moderate, never taxed by God as his faults; and if this muſt be aſſigned a juſt cauſe for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance, that they were governed by a Man, not by an Angel, by one ſubject to humane infirmities like themſelves, all the World would be in a flame, and none left to rule in peace. What has the Subject to do with the private failings of his Prince? He that was King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was accountable to none but the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and therefore he ſays, <hi>Pſal.</hi> li. 4. <hi>Againſt thee, thee only have I ſinned;</hi> and well he might ſay ſo, for as to the people entruſted to his charge, he was ſo upright and diſcreet in the managing his honour and power that he gave them no offence: So equal in his Juſtice, ſo obliging in his Favours, that he committed no fault againſt them. And ſo I paſs to the laſt particular propoſed, <hi>Davids</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to praiſe God for delivering of him, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto thee, O my ſtrength, will I ſing: For thou, O God, art my refuge, and my merciful God.</hi> Where we may obſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">I. The Perſon reſolving, and that is <hi>David, I will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. Of what he reſolves; and that is to ſing: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto thee, O my ſtrength, will I ſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. The reaſon of this his Reſolution, <hi>For thou, O God, art my refuge, and my merciful God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>I will,</hi> (ſays this holy King) and it was but his duty; he in the firſt place, he to lead the way, he to give the example. The deliverances were publick, and he a publick perſon, and ſo more concerned in them than any other; yet all obliged too as well as he, though not in ſo high a degree, even in thoſe dangers that aimed only at his Perſon: As the Members for the Head, if that be wounded, all ſuffer with it. And that the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36564:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were very ſenſible of this; ſee what an eſteem they ſet upon <hi>Davids</hi> preſervation, (2 <hi>Sam.</hi> xviii. 3.) when that unnatural <hi>Abſolom</hi> had blown the Trumpet of Rebellion, and the warlike King was once more reſolved to give his Subjects a further proof of his perſonal va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour: <hi>Thou ſhalt not go forth; for if we flee away, they will not care for us, neither if half of us die will they care for us; but now thou art worth ten thouſands, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is better that thou ſuccour us out of the City:</hi> If the King be ſafe, the Nation is ſecure; and when he has cauſe to ſing, if he ſay, <hi>I will;</hi> it is then a ſhame and folly too, as well as ſin, for the Subjects to be ſilent, ſo to mind our Private, as if we had no relation to the Publick; no obligation to mourn for to endeavour to remove National Calamities: Or to ſing and rejoyce for publick mercies and deliverances, ſince that is each par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars intereſt, and therefore as every man is concerned in the benefit, every man muſt betake himſelf to the duty; that is thankfulneſs, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto thee, O my ſtrength, will I ſing.</hi> The next particular.</p>
            <p>If Gratitude be within, ſomething will appear with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out; if there be that apprehenſion, that eſtimation of the bleſſing as it deſerves, it cannot be kept ſhut in the heart, no more than fire in the boſom. Gods glory and his delivering from dangers will make a good man ſpeak, even when terrour it ſelf hath commanded ſilence. In <hi>Luke</hi> xi. 14. our Saviour caſt out a dumb devil, and the dumb ſpake, and the people wondred. Many are poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed (I am afraid in this Age of ours) with this dumb devil: So that to hear one of them ſing forth the praiſes of the Almighty for his deliverances, would make all the people wonder. The Tongue was principally gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven (you know) to ſet forth his praiſe and glory, and it concerns us to uſe it accordingly; we offend, we pull down Judgments by it, and it is but meet we give thanks
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36564:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>with it for our deliverances, elſe we have but dull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments of his Favours. And therefore ſays this Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prophet, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto thee, O my ſtrength, will I ſing: For thou, O God, art my refuge, and my merciful God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>David</hi> look'd upon God to be his <hi>Aſylum,</hi> his refuge, and his only ſanctuary of defence, his many <hi>Pſalms</hi> (penned as the records of his gratitude) ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently enform us. <hi>Deliver me,</hi> (ſays he, <hi>Pſal.</hi> xxxiv. 19.) <hi>O God, for vain is the help of man;</hi> And in the height of diſtreſs he cries out, (<hi>Pſal.</hi> xxv. 22.) <hi>Deliver Iſrael, O God, out of all his troubles.</hi> It was <hi>Rabſhakehs</hi> blaſphemy, <hi>Iſa.</hi> xxxvi. 20. <hi>What God can deliver out of my hand?</hi> What God? He found it to his coſt. Till <hi>Lot</hi> be eſcaped, not a ſpark muſt kindle. The impartial Sword muſt not touch <hi>Rahab,</hi> nor the deſtroying Angel offer a blow to the ſprinkled doors. Thoſe Miniſters of Juſtice (<hi>Ezek.</hi> ix. 4.) have an Inkhorn as well as a Sword: An Inkhorn, firſt to mark the choſen, and then to go and ſmite. It were endleſs to multiply proofs out of Scriptures, which are but the Regiſters of his Providence, and you cannot look beſides them there. And it is no leſs apparent unto reaſon, for that finds there is a God, and from thence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes a Providence. So that ſhould I lead you out of the Church into the Schools of the Heathens of all ſorts, you will find them, by the very inſtinct and light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, aſſerting the ſame truth; ever aſcribing all good ſucceſſes to their <hi>Daemons,</hi> and accordingly giving thanks, courting them with Sacrifices, and Holy days, dreſſing their Images with Garlands, and devoting part of their ſpoils taken for the maintenance of their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and making magnificent their Temples.</p>
            <p>But unto what times, O Lord, haſt thou reſerved us? For to our great ſhame and greater grief be it ſpoken, Have we not ſome in theſe days (I fear many) more heatheniſh than the Heathens, who will not allow God to govern in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36564:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>his own Houſe, to have the managery of his own Family, that deny his taking care of things below; and having the confidence to aſſert, that he is ſo far from delivering us from dangers, that he takes no cognizance how we come in, or how we get out. A perſwaſion that thwarts the common Notions of mankind, that deſtroys, that confounds the advancement of all noble reſolutions, that wholly makes void and ridiculous the duty we are about, and indeed all other; for it is totally deſtructive of all Vertue, Religion, and Government; none of which can ſubſiſt, or be long lived, without a belief, a ſenſe, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence of ſome Divine Power, that does not only protect, guard, and defend us from dangers, but that will be ſure to call for an account of our acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>Yet theſe muſt be cried up for the Vertuoſo's, the Wits of the Age. It is ſtrange, it was not ſo thought of old, and let who will admire them, <hi>David</hi> ſets a Fools Cap upon their heads, <hi>Pſal.</hi> xiv. 1. <hi>The fool hath ſaid in his heart, there is no God,</hi> that is, (as the word there ſignifies) no Judge, no Providence, and I hope you will not think the term uncivil, it is not mine, but his. And would they but have recourſe to their own Conſciences; conſult thoſe indeleble Letters there engraven, and never to be raſed out, they muſt (however puft up with pride, and aiming to be ſingular, and different in Paradoxiſm from all the world) acknowledge that there is a good provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence over them, that orders all the Affairs of the world, from the leaſt to the greateſt, from Crowns and Scepters to the falling of a Sparrow on the ground, and the very numbring of their hairs, and joyn with holy <hi>David,</hi> and ſay, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto thee, O my ſtrength, will I ſing: For thou, O God, art my refuge, and my merciful God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having taken a view of <hi>Davids</hi> Innocency, and the malice of his Enemies, together with Gods delivering of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36564:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>him, and his thankfulneſs. Let me now beg your pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and attention, to ſee how our gracious King runs parallel, not only with him in his dangers, but in his deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances too.</p>
            <p>And firſt, as <hi>David</hi> having been oft delivered not only from the private deſigns of his Enemies, but when their Rebellion was grown to that height, and power, as to force him from his Throne; was brought back again by the powerful arm of Heaven, had good reaſon to ſtile the Almighty not only God, but his God. So ſurely no Prince ſince <hi>Adams</hi> Creation, ever had greater proofs of an Omnipotent Protection, than our now meſt gracious Sovereign. How diligent, how vigilant was Heaven in the ſecuring of him, (when our Nation was in a flame of Rebellion) from his Enemies; who prized his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction more than their own preſervation: And had not a more than ordinary Providence provided for his eſcape, how had his Royal bloud been ſacrificed as an Allay to their unheard-of Cruelty?</p>
            <p>But above all, that of his miraculous Reſtauration, when his Adverſaries thought themſelves in ſecure poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, when Church and State, Religion and Learning, Laws and Liberty, were not only in danger, but already devoured in the hope and expectation of his Enemies; when Atheiſm and Ignorance were in a full and fierce torrent breaking in upon his Dominions, and we his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects at the very brink of a remedileſs Confuſion, fit Objects either for the pity, or the ſcorn of the World, as they ſtood affected to us; then, even then (when nothing but faith, and that of the taller ſort too, could ſee any appearance of him) did Heaven (to the wonder and amazement of the world) place him on the Throne of his Fathers. All which may juſtly intitle him when in danger, as well as <hi>David,</hi> to ſay, <hi>Deliver me, O my God; for lo, they lie waiting for my Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:36564:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Now for Policy, the next Parallel, his Majeſties Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies that lie waiting for his Soul, clearly out-vie, and out-do King <hi>Davids:</hi> Alas they (in thoſe more early days of Impiety) were never acquainted with ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances and ſtratagems; as the old Gentleman of <hi>Rome</hi> (by his Agents the Jeſuits) teaches his Creatures in theſe of ours: Who put on all the formalities of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and merit when they intend to murther. Making good that Prediction of our ever bleſſed Saviour, <hi>They ſhall kill you, and think they do God good ſervice.</hi> And have they not turned their Pens into Pen-knives, multiplied the School into a Camp, Arguments to Armies, teaching all their Proſelytes diſmal Concluſions.</p>
            <p>Indeed, what mask do they not make uſe of to deſtroy, and promote faction? Obſerving that Maxim of their old Roman Maſters, <hi>Divide &amp; impera;</hi> and to this end have they not been, nay, are they not Presbyterians, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, Libertines, Pagans, any thing, ſo they be not Subjects. Moſt, if not all the ſtorms, that have been rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Chriſtendom, ſince <hi>Charlemains</hi> time, are owing to the Pope and his Miniſters. And I hope it will be no digreſſion (for the King of <hi>England</hi> never dies) to let you ſee, how induſtrious they have been in all Ages, to bring this Nation under the Romiſh ſlavery, ten times worſe than that of <hi>Egypt.</hi> And though our Kings have been more kind and generous Vaſſals than any of their Neighbours, though they were as obedient Sons as any that ever owned St. <hi>Peters</hi> Keys, as liberal in their erecting and endowing Churches and Monaſteries as any Princes in the world; as the many ſtately and magnificent Structures (before the hammers of their own impieties rung their paſſing-knels) in each corner of the Land did (and their ruines ſtill do) ſufficiently witneſs, yet none have been ſo ungratefully requited as they: No Crown ſuffered ſo much ignominy and bondage under the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36564:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>Tyranny of the Roman Prelate, as this of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For no ſooner had the munificent Monarchs of this Nation, built ſo many famous Fabricks, but the Pope claimed the inveſting and Collating of them. Not that the Church might be better provided for; but that by Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery and Simony he might enrich his Treaſury; of which (though many inſtances might be given) let that of <hi>Walter Gray</hi> (ſet down by a Monk of their own) ſpeak for all the reſt;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth. Paris</hi> in <hi>Johan.</hi> p. 263.</note> who for his inveſtiture at <hi>Rome</hi> obliged himſelf to pay to the Pope ten thouſand pounds ſterling, in thoſe days enough for a Kings Ranſom.</p>
            <p>This was the end for which the Pope had uſed ſo many Policies, taking the advantage of the neceſſities of Kings, and their rebellious Subjects. This was it for which ſo much bloud had been ſhed, for which above an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſet Battels were fought ſince <hi>Gregory</hi> VII. This was it for which thoſe that ſuffered in the Popes claim for it, were ſtiled Martyrs, put into the Liſt of Saints, and were ſure to do Miracles after their death.</p>
            <p>This was it which made <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the Second eſpouſe the Intereſt of <hi>Anſelm,</hi> who was fled from his own Prince, <hi>William Rufus,</hi> and liking the prudence of that Fugitive, made uſe of his Counſel, and gave him the Archbiſhops Pall, thereby voiding the Inveſtiture he had received from the King his Maſter; and obliging him (with the gift of that he had nothing to do with) to a depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency on him: And what diſturbances followed both to King and State,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth. Paris</hi> in <hi>Guliel. Rufo.</hi>
               </note> the above-cited Monk has largely ſet down.</p>
            <p>Neither did this quarrel die with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> and King <hi>William,</hi> for no ſooner had <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt of that name aſcended the Throne, and <hi>Paſchal</hi> the Second ſeated him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in St. <hi>Peters</hi> Chair, but he juſtified (as well as his Predeceſſor) the Archbiſhop in his Rebellion againſt his Sovereign, and ſends him a <hi>Mandate</hi> to declare, that no
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36564:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>Lay man ſhould have power to confer any Inveſtiture: Upon which (this Biſhop devoted to the <hi>Roman</hi> Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt) began to degrade his Brethren, promoted by the Kings nomination, and refuſed to Conſecrate others named by him. At which the King (as he had good reaſon) being angry, baniſhed him out of his Kingdom. But how this was reſented at <hi>Rome,</hi> and what troubles enſued thereupon to this Realm, the Hiſtorians of that Age have ſadly recorded.</p>
            <p>After <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt came <hi>Stephen,</hi> and after him <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, A potent and warlike Prince, who beſides <hi>England,</hi> held <hi>Normandy, Anjou, Poitou,</hi> &amp;c. Yet this potent King was ſtrangely diſquieted by <hi>Thomas Becket</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> A man abundantly ſtored with an ambitious, turbulent, and ungrateful Spirit, as appeared by his diſowning the Inveſtiture of the King, by whoſe favour and bounty he was promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and receiving his Pall from the Pope. At which the King, being enraged, exiled him out of him Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions; but he fled to <hi>Rome,</hi> (the Sanctuary in thoſe days always open for ſuch Traitors) where he was not only entertained, (to the great grief of the King) but countenanced, encouraged, and bid hearthy welcom by Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the Third, who vindicated the quarrel (for indeed it was his own) at ſo high a rate, that this great Prince, partly through neceſſity, and fear of the power of the Keys, (which made wonderful clinking in thoſe times) and partly being perſwaded by ſome Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth. Paris</hi> In <hi>Hen. Secund.</hi> p. 117.</note> gave this Archbiſhop a meeting (in hopes of a reconciliation) at <hi>Froncevaux,</hi> and did that which no man would have believed, for he held the Bridle of <hi>Beckets</hi> horſe, and that proud Prelate not contented to have received the honour once, alighted on purpoſe that the King ſhould pay him ſubmiſſion twice, as he alſo did. Thus that Prieſt practiſed Apoſtolick humility.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:36564:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>After this Triumph highly applauded at <hi>Rome, Becket</hi> returned into <hi>England</hi> full of glory: Where inſtead of bringing Peace, he was the Bearer and Proclaimer of an Excommunication, and Sentence of depoſition of the Archbiſhop of <hi>York</hi> and his Adherents, for Crowning the young King in his abſence.</p>
            <p>The King being in <hi>Normandy,</hi> and hearing of theſe procedures of the Archbiſhops, ſent four of his Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants to require him to abſolve thoſe he had ſo unjuſtly excommunicated, and take off his Suſpenſions from others. Which command he refuſing to obey, the King began to lament his condition. This moved the ſame four whom he had ſent before, to return into <hi>England,</hi> and finding the Archbiſhop in the Church of <hi>Canterbury</hi> (ſome ſay at the High Altar) at three a clockiin the Afternoon, calling him Traitor, ſlew him.</p>
            <p>No ſooner did the news of this arrive, King <hi>Henry</hi> ſtill in <hi>Normandy,</hi> but he ſhew'd a great deal of ſorrow for it, and though he proteſted his innocency as to the fact, yet he ſent an Embaſſie to the Pope, to make ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. But the teſty old man was ſo enraged, that he would not ſo much as vouchſafe his Embaſſadours to kiſs his feet, but in great wrath ſpake of Interdicting the whole Kingdom, which (in thoſe days) was looked upon as the ſending all the Engliſh into Hell. The dread of which forced this Magnanimous King to buy his Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution at a dear rate; acquitting not only his right of inveſting, but likewiſe engaging to keep two hundred men of Arms in pay, for the ſervice of the Holy War, and the Popes Aſſigns to be the receivers. And to make the ſatifaction compleat, the Majeſty of this great Monarch (to the wonder of the world) muſt be ſo far debaſed, as to be ſtript naked, and whipt by a company of Monks. And that ſuch Rebels as <hi>Becket</hi> might never want encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement in ſucceeding Ages, the Pope did not only
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36564:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>defend him whilſt he lived, but Canoniz'd him when he was dead.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Henry</hi> being gathered to his Fathers, his Son <hi>Richard</hi> (ſurnamed <hi>Cor de Lion</hi>) ſucceeded him, not only in his Throne, but in his troubles too. That Prince for the better ſecuring <hi>Normandy,</hi> was reſolved to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the Caſtle of <hi>Andeli:</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Mat. Paris,</hi> p. 175.</note> At which <hi>Walter</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Rouen</hi> being diſpleaſed, immediately Interdicts all <hi>Normandy;</hi> and flies to <hi>Rome,</hi> where he found as kind entertainment as ever <hi>Becket</hi> did. And now, what muſt the King do? Alas ſubmit; to conteſt was in vain, for ſuch was the fear of an Interdict in thoſe times, that there was nothing which the Pope could not obtain of Princes and Nations, if he did but threaten them with it.</p>
            <p>But above all, that in the Reign of King <hi>John</hi> was the moſt diſmal, when <hi>England</hi> remained under the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict ſix years, three months, and an half. Not only the King and his Court, but all the People of the Nation were Excommunicated, and that not for Hereſie, not for any Crime of theirs; but for a quarrel between the King and the Pope, about Inveſtitures, Collations, and Money matters.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth. Paris</hi> in <hi>Johan.</hi> p. 217.</note> Then (ſaith <hi>Matthew Paris,</hi> who was an Eye-witneſs of all that diſorder) all the Sacraments of the Church ceaſed in <hi>England,</hi> ſaving only the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and Communion of the Hoſt in the laſt neceſſity, and Baptiſm of little Children. Then were the Dead carried out of Towns, as if they had been Dogs, and buried in High-ways and Ditches; without Prayers, and without Service of Prieſts.</p>
            <p>Yet this not producing the end it was deſigned for, the <hi>Balaam</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> proceeds to curſe the King by name; and finally, to pronounce ſentence of Depoſition againſt him; diſcharging all his Subjects of their Oaths of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance; and ſends his Legat to <hi>Philip Anguſt,</hi> King of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36564:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>France,</hi> that for the remiſſion of his ſins, he ſhould invade the Realm of <hi>England</hi> with force of Arms, and giving to all thoſe that would attend him in that Conqueſt, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of all theirs, and the ſame graces as to them that viſit the Holy Sepulchre: Whereupon <hi>Philip</hi> to obtain pardon of his ſins (or rather to make himſelf Maſter of this Land) raiſed a mighty Army, whilſt <hi>Innocent</hi> (by his Creatures) was labouring to engage the Engliſh againſt their own King. By this means King <hi>John</hi> was ſtrangely and ſuddenly weakned, and utterly diſabled to hold his Kingdom, and ſeeing ſtrong invaſions from without, and daily revoltings within to open Inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and every man now counted a Saint and Martyr that would fight againſt him; and conſidering that the Popes Bulls, like Magick Spells, had let looſe many tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent Spirits, not to be laid again, but by him that rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them. After much debate, and with a heart full of anguiſh and rage, at laſt reſolves to proſtitute his Crown and Dignity to <hi>Pandulph</hi> the Legate, that he might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it again from him, as from the Popes hands, and be protected by him. Thus the Pope taking advantage of this poor Princes miſery, made him a Vaſſal to his own greatneſs, and his Kingdom a prop to uphold St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> Chair.</p>
            <p>For theſe pretended Succeſſors of that great Apoſtle, fiſh not for Souls, but for Empire, even with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Millions (if their own Doctrine be true) which ſays that all that die under the Interdict (without ſome ſpecial grace or priviledge, and that not to be had without ready money) are eternally damned, as dying out of the Communion of the Church. So that if St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould now come to his Succeſſor in his old tone, <hi>Silver and Gold have I none,</hi> if he were a thouſand <hi>Peters,</hi> he muſt into Purgatory.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:36564:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>How many Millions then of Souls, did this <hi>Innocent</hi> the Pope wilfully ſend to Hell in this great Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> in the Space of above ſix years? And this for no offence, no fault of theirs: For what could they do, if the King would not be ruled by the Pope? Are theſe the actions of the Vicar of Chriſt? Is this the kind Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Church? Is this the way of managing the Keys? Yes, he that conſults the Reigns of our ſucceeding Kings, from the time of King <hi>John</hi> to our own (which would make me too great a debtor to your patience particularly to relate) ſhall find, that no ſtone has been left unturn'd, no policies (though never ſo horrid) have not been put in execution, to reduce this Nation to that miſerable ſlavery they had once impoſed upon it.</p>
            <p>For it is not for the Points of true Doctrine, but for Wealth and Grandeur, for the ſetting up of their viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Monarchy of the Church (whereof Chriſt and his Apoſtles never ſpake a word, and of which the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Fathers never dreamt) they ſo much contend. <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth held all the Doctrinal Points of the Romiſh Religion, yet for rejecting the Juriſdiction of <hi>Rome,</hi> was Excommunicated by the Pope, his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects commanded to deny obedience, and all men to take Arms againſt him. This is it, which if our Religion would allow,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pius</hi> IV. <hi>Hiſt. Conc. Trid.</hi> lib. 8. p. 7.5.</note> they would allow of our Religion. The Politick rather than Pious Pope ſaid once: Since he could not regain the Proteſtants, it was neceſſary to keep thoſe in obedience which he had, to make the diviſion ſtrong, and the parties irreconcilable. Conformable whereunto their now Doctrine is, that ſuch as ſubmit not to the Popes Supremacy do renounce Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity.</p>
            <p>When the Fires of Queen <hi>Maries</hi> bloudy Reign could not do this work, how many Plots were laid againſt the life of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> that Queen of bleſſed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36564:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>memory, by whoſe gracious hand God wrought thoſe wonders, that the moſt potent Kings can hardly reach, Honour filled the Circle of her Crown, her brow with Majeſty, her heart with Piety, and her lap with Plenty. Yet how execrable were the Treaſons againſt that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Defender of the Faith, and of her Royal Rights? When neither the Dagger nor the Poyſon could reach her Sacred Perſon, an invincible Armado (as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſtiled it) muſt be ſent to invade <hi>England,</hi> three Popes having made way for the Sword, by three roaring Bulls, which dethroned the Queen, and commanded her Subjects to take Arms againſt her. But when the invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible Army had loſt that name, being defeated by the powerful Arm of God, other Armies were poured from time to time into <hi>Ireland,</hi> ever prone to Rebel. When all thoſe effects were fruſtrated, God bleſſing <hi>England</hi> becauſe the Popes curſed it, and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> full of days and glory, was tranſlated from a Temporal, to an Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Diadem; her peaceful Succeſſor, Defender of the ſame holy Faith, muſt be welcomed to his Throne by a Mandate of <hi>Clement</hi> the VIII. declaring him unworthy to ſit there, as an Heretick, and forbidding his Subjects to obey him.</p>
            <p>When all that would not effect the deſired end, to make ſhort work, ſuch a device is excogitated as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>Rome</hi> and the Devil could have invented: And now they are reſolved on that deſperate Cry, <hi>Incendium extinguatur ruina,</hi> the King and his Royal Iſſue, Lords and Commons, all the flower and vigour of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom muſt be blown up, ſent to heaven before the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. Bloudy Prieſts, that would have offered a whole burnt Sacrifice, and made both Prince and Peers paſs through the fire, an oblation to their <hi>Moloch</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:36564:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And as for our late King of bleſſed memory, that Prince in whoſe breaſt all thoſe Vertues Centred, which ſeverally had commended the great Monarchs of former Ages. Was he not beholden (as it is now apparent) to his Holineſs, for raiſing all thoſe ſtorms of Rebellion, upon the face of his calm Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hoping in thoſe troubled waters to have catch'd that Fiſh, he had been Angling for ſo many Ages.</p>
            <p>Indeed, the large claim of St. <hi>Peters</hi> Regalities, has been for theſe laſt ſix hundred years, the cauſe of all the Corruptions of Faith and Religion, of all the Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Diſtractions, of all the Seditions and Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions in the Weſt of the world. And we of this Iſland (by ſad experience) have been taught, that this is the great Wheel, that ſets thoſe Miſchiefs, Plots, and Treaſons on going, wherewith the State hath been ſo many times ſhaken; torn, and brought to the brink of ruine.</p>
            <p>For when hot-headed Zealots are really perſwaded, that the Pope has power to depoſe Emperours and Kings that oppoſe him, and abſolve Subjects from their Allegiance to them (and this believed as abſolutely neceſſary to Salvation) what Royal bloud will they ſpare? What attempt, be it never ſo cruel, never ſo unjuſt, never ſo difficult, will they not aſſay, to bring their Country under the Popes ſubjection, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote his Univerſal Monarchy? Or can it be expected they will deſiſt from endeavouring its reducement, (though after the moſt inhumane and barbarous way, that any thing but <hi>Rome</hi> and Hell ever thought of) ſo long as the Pope (whoſe ſlaves they are) is himſelf a ſlave to his own cruel and illimited Ambition, which to ſatiate all the Kingdoms, and all the bloud in the world are too little.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:36564:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And never was it more evident, more apparent to the world (than in this late diſcovered Conſpiracy againſt our moſt gracious Sovereign) what their reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are, and what both King and People muſt expect from the <hi>Roman</hi> Prelate; whoſe malice never ſleeps, nor whoſe Agents never reſt to work his Ruine, ſo that he may ſay of them (and juſtly too) as King <hi>David</hi> did of his, <hi>They are minded to do me ſome miſchief, ſo maliciouſly are they bent againſt me.</hi> But we will paſs from their Malice and Policy, to a conſideration of their Might and Power, the next in order: <hi>The mighty men are gathered againſt me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The mighty!</hi> alas he is ſuch in the Superlative degree (that is enemy to his Majeſty) if you will believe him for this, he that aſſerts, that all Empires and Scepters are at his diſpoſe. As <hi>Pius</hi> the Fifth taught the People of this Kingdom in expreſs words, in the Bull of Depriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which he thundred againſt Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> And to make this good to the world, and to ſhew the height of his Pride, Pope <hi>Celeſtine</hi> crowned <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth Emperour of that name with his feet, and kickt it off when he had done, making no leſs than an Emperours Crown his Foot-ball. <hi>Gregory</hi> the Seventh made <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth pay attendance at his Gates in Winter four days bare-footed. And <hi>Alexander</hi> the Third with an inſulting ſcorn trode on the Neck of <hi>Frederick Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baroſa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is he that can give and take Heaven away at his pleaſure,
<note place="margin">Mat. 4.9.</note> a Priviledge that great Uſurper his Father never challenged. Nay,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cerem. Sacra.</hi> l. 1. §. 7. c. 6.</note> this is he that has encroach'd upon the higheſt Prerogatives and Titles of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the Fourth (out of his ſingular mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty) aſſumed that authority, which not only we, but all the Primitive Chriſtians thought to belong to Chriſt alone; <hi>All power is given me both in heaven and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36564:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>Earth.</hi> Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Second was ſtiled a Celeſtial Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, which all know is only proper to God. Pope <hi>Sixtus Quintus</hi> called the Corner-ſtone in <hi>Sion,</hi> due to the Son of God. And in the laſt Council of <hi>Lateran</hi> it was decreed, that the Pope muſt be adored by all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and that he is moſt like unto God. Yea, we are further told in the ſame place, that he muſt be adored with the ſame Adoration enjoyned, <hi>Pſal.</hi> lxii. <hi>All the Kings of the earth ſhall worſhip him;</hi> in which Text the Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion proper to our ever-bleſſed Saviour is underſtood, and ſo it is taken by <hi>Tertullian.</hi> So that if <hi>David</hi> were permitted to ſpeak from the dead, he muſt needs acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and ſay, that thoſe of his (though mighty) were far inferiour to theſe enemies of his Majeſty. Which brings me to the next conſiderable, <hi>Without any offence or fault of me, O Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And does not our gracious King run parallel with him in this? What Prince ever writ his favours in ſuch en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging Characters as he has done? That were his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries any thing but what they are (Vaſſals to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> greatneſs) he muſt for ever have endeared and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured their obedience. A Prince whoſe unſpotted In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency is ſuch, that no fancies or fears diſturb his breaſt; for as he is guilty of nothing, ſo there is nothing he dreads. He is the very Compound of Charity and Compaſſion: For he pities thoſe that will not pity them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and whilſt they contrive his deſtruction, his Prayers aſcend heaven for their pardon? Nor can the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of their malice provoke him to a retaliation, having learnt not only of God, but the King his Father to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give his very Enemies.</p>
            <p>Now to ſtudy, to deſign and plot the ruine of ſuch a Prince, muſt make a ſtrange aggravation of the Crime; and render the Conſpirators much more black, not only to this, but to all ſucceeding Ages; eſpecially when they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36564:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhall find that ſome of them were indebted to his boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for their bread. O, but he will not admit of the power of our Father the Pope, and all Obligements, all Oaths, all that is Sacred are too weak to engage and bind our Loyalty, when he claims not only Rivality, but Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy. And therefore (Great Sir) pardon us, we will ſerve you in any thing elſe; but when that Intereſt is on foot, when he enjoyns and commands us, we are bound (and that under no leſs penalty than eternal damnation) to deveſt our ſelves of all to promote it.</p>
            <p>Is this the cauſe, is this his offence, is this his fault? What if the Pope command his Majeſty to break the Sacred Mandates of the Almighty, and kneel before an Idol, and offer his Invocation unto others than God? What if he appoint him other Redeemers than Chriſt, and other merits for his Propitiation, than thoſe of his obedience in the Death of the Croſs? What if contrary to the Apoſtle he tell him, that the Bloud of Jeſus clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him not from all ſin, and will ſend him to be cleanſed in an imaginary fire of Purgatory, and fright his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to drain his Purſe? Muſt he, to pleaſe the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matchable pride and inſatiable griping of that Tyrant, hood wink his Reaſon, befool his Conſcience, make ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack of his Faith, and blindly and wilfully inſlave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and his Subjects under the yoke of the Romiſh bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage? Or elſe be depoſed and murthered, and his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms diſpoſed of at the Popes pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Good God! how contrary is this to the Religion of the ever bleſſed Jeſus, to the practice of his Apoſtles, and the Primitive times? Our Saviour himſelf was ſo far from pretending to a diſpoſal of temporal Empires; that he refuſed to divide Inheritances among Brethren, as a thing that belonged not to him, in <hi>Luke</hi> xii. 14. And for the Apoſtles, how earneſtly did they exhort and perſuade
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36564:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>their Auditors to be obedient, not only for wrath, but for Conſcience ſake. Not becauſe the Emperours had their Swords in their hands, and might therefore puniſh them; but becauſe God did command and require it of them. That known paſſage of St. <hi>Paul</hi> may ſerve for an abundant evidence, <hi>Rom.</hi> xiii. 2. where he not only affirms, <hi>That whoſoever reſiſteth the power, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God,</hi> but alſo <hi>that they that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that the ancient Chriſtians were of the ſame temper with their Maſter and his Apoſtles ſubmitting themſelves to the penalties of thoſe Laws, whoſe Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions they thought it not lawful to obſerve, is clear from <hi>Tertullian</hi> and others. And this they did too, not (as that great Cardinal would have the world believe) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they wanted force and power to reſiſt;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bel.</hi> lib. 5. <hi>de Rom. Pont.</hi> cap. 4. &amp; 7.</note> but in a real practice of the Precepts of the ever bleſſed Jeſus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> and <hi>Cyprian,</hi> two Ancient Fathers, being under the Perſecution of the heathen Emperours, do make their Apologies in behalf of the Chriſtian and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tertal. Apol. contra Gentes.</hi> cap. 37.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> thus: <q rend="inline">God forbid that our Chriſtian Profeſſion ſhould be revenged by Humane Power, or ſhould grieve to ſuffer that whereby we are tried: Although if we would become either ſecret or open revengers of our own wrongs, could we want either number or power? What War is there that we are not fit for, yea, and ready alſo to undertake, if that our Religion taught us not rather to be killed, than to kill for the profeſſion thereof?</q>
               <note place="margin">Cyprian ad Demetr.</note> And St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">Our Profeſſors (ſaith he) do not take revenge againſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt violence, though our people be more in number.</q> And agreeing hereto when the <hi>Theban</hi> Legion, which conſiſted of ſix thouſand, ſix hundred ſixty ſix Chriſtian Souldiers, were by the Emperour <hi>Maximian</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:36564:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>to offer Sacrifice to the heathen Gods, though they refuſed to obey his commands, yet when he upon that refuſal, commanded every tenth man to be ſlain, they ſuffered themſelves ſo to be without any the leaſt reſiſtance; looking upon themſelves as obliged by their Religion, to obey him either actively or paſſively.</p>
            <p>Thus the Supremacy and Power in thoſe days was in the Emperours, and Obedience was held better than Sacrifice: And this owned and practiſed by ſeveral of the Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> themſelves, as <hi>Binius</hi> and <hi>Baronius</hi> (two Witneſſes againſt whom I hope they will take no excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) have ſet down, yet I ſhall only produce three of them, that number having always looked upon (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of ſuch men) ſufficient for any Teſt. And the firſt is Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the firſt who made his addreſſes to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, that the Emperour would be pleaſed to command a Synod to be celebrated in <hi>Italy,</hi> and (though he did it by all the ways of humility) could not obtain it. The next is Pope <hi>Pelagius</hi> the Firſt, who aſſerted that by holy Scripture (then adjuſted as the rule of faith and manners) they were commanded to be ſubject to Kings. The third is Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> the firſt, who devoted himſelf to the Emperour by Letters, as one in ſupplication fallen down proſtrate at the ſoles of his feet. That baſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Princes kiſſing the Popes Toe being not then known to the world.</p>
            <p>It was a thouſand years after Chriſt, before St. <hi>Peters</hi> temporal Sword was found, unſheath'd and flouriſhed to fright Kings out of their Authority and Power, and what horrid means have they uſed (it having laid ruſting ſo long) to make it bright, deluding and inebriating the people with falſe opinions, perſwading them to drink down Poyſon, inſtead of wholſom Doctrine, to break the moſt manifeſt and poſitive Laws of God at the Popes command. How ſtrongly do the Precepts of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:36564:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>bind us to an obedience to all that are in Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Power? How has he hedged in Regality, ſaying, <hi>Touch not mine Anointed?</hi> That one would think nothing could be more ſafe. Yet alas, how has this wild Boar out of the Fofreſt broke down all thoſe Fences? Tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his Devotaries, that he hath power to abſolve them from all their Oaths of Allegiance to their King the Lords Anointed, and declaring they ought rather to obey him than God. That it is no matter, nay, though St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf gave it in charge, and that for Conſcience ſake, as acceptable to heaven, (1 <hi>Pet.</hi> ii. 17.) not only to <hi>fear God,</hi> but to <hi>honour the King:</hi> Thereby plainly intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that it is impoſſible to be true Servants to God, without being Loyal Subjects to the King, ſo long as he ſays, Rebel againſt Princes who will not own my Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, and for Conſcience ſake (though contrary to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and common honeſty) work Treaſons, Inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Maſſacres, and what not, for that is acceptable to God.</p>
            <p>What new incredible abominable Doctrine is this? That firing Cities, Treaſons, Rebellions, dethroning of Princes, adjudging their Kingdoms to ſtrangers, filling the World with Perjuries, Wars, Invaſions, bringing in a Chaos of Confuſion, and the face of Hell into the Chriſtian world, ſhould be meritorious, a work of Piety and Religion!</p>
            <p>Yet is not this preached up by the Jeſuits, eſpouſed and faithfully believed and practiſed by the Romaniſts? Could the Martyrs of his Holineſs ſpeak to us from their Aſhes under the Gallows, how would they tell us that what they did, was in obedience to the Father of their Faith the Pope, whoſe Mandate did inſtruct and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage them to do it; upon him then, upon that your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied enemy, lay the greateſt burden of the infamy. Look to ſhield your heads from the deſigns of the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:36564:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>living, and leave the dead in the hands of Gods Juſtice. For be aſſured that though we are cut off, he will not want ſome Sons as blindly zealous as we were, who for the hopes of a Canonization, will refuſe the executing of no Treaſon, though never ſo horrid, never ſo blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, nay, though againſt Princes by whom they have been never ſo much obliged. And that this is their Creed and Practice; was there ever a more clear demonſtration to the world. than in this damnable Piot againſt his Sacred Majeſty, which Heaven (in deſpite of all their ſeeret contrivances) has been pleaſed to lay open to their ſhame, (if they be capable of any) and our comfort. Which brings me to the laſt particular propoſed by way of Parallel, <hi>Davids</hi> reſolution to praiſe God for delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of him.</p>
            <p>Now in this as well as in the reſt, our King is reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not to be behind King <hi>David,</hi> having commanded to blow the Trumpet in <hi>Zion,</hi> and ſanctifie a Faſt, a Trumpet worthy of Royal breath, having ſet this day apart to bleſs God for his mercies already beſtowed, and by an early and timely repentance (in and through the bloud of the ever bleſſed Jeſus) to engage a further continuance of them: Never was it, never can it be more ſeaſonable than now. Now when our God has done ſo great things for his Anointed, delivering from his enemies, whoſe Malice is not to be defeated, and whoſe ſecret Combinations are not to be diſcovered, but by his goodneſs, who never ſlumbers nor ſleeps in our prefervation. Ask from Eaſt to Weſt, conſult the days of old, and ſee if ever God has appeared more vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly for any Nation than this of ours.</p>
            <p>How did he ſcatter that daring Armado in Eighty Eight, (not only to the wonder of our Allies, but to the Amazement of our Enemies, which made ſome of them (though blaſphemouſly) ſay, <hi>That God
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:36564:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>himſelf was turned Lutheran</hi>) whoſe prodigious weight ſeemed to make the very Waves groan with its inſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table burden?</p>
            <p>How did he (in the days of King <hi>James</hi>) lay open thoſe <hi>Penetralia mortis,</hi> thoſe inward Chambers, and receſſes of death? Their ſecreſie made them confident, engaging their Agents with all that is looked upon as Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, Religion, Oath, and Sacrament not to reveal it, eating their God upon a bargain of bloud.</p>
            <p>How did he, when they (by raiſing thoſe late uncivil Civil Wars and diſſenſions among us) hoped to have made us fallen by our own Swords, make us happy in his Majeſties return? And to endear our gratitude, how is he reſolved (as it is evident by the diſcovery of this late moſt deteſtable Conſpiracy) ſtill to defend (maugre all their envy and malice) <hi>the Great Defender of the Faith?</hi> So that if we have not abſolutely taken leave of our Underſtandings, if our ſpirits be not quite beſotted, we muſt ſay with holy <hi>David, What ſhall we return unto the Lord, for all his benefits done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What indeed, O God! for delivering us from a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that (contrary to all thy Precepts in the Old, and the Doctrine and Example of thy Son in the New Teſtament) commands us to Worſhip Images, Adore Reliques, Invoke Saints, Sacrifice for the ſins of the living and the dead, hold a Purgatory (as if the bloud of the ever bleſſed Jeſus was not able to do it) for the cleanſing of Souls; tread down thy Viceroys from their Thrones, and ſet up an uſurping Prelate, who by the conſent of all Ages, has been acknowledged a Vaſſal to Princes; in ſhort, from a Religion that would take away the Scriptures, (thoſe Sacred Legacies of thine to the Sons of men) and wrap up our Conſciences in the livery of an unknown Language; that licenſes
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:36564:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>Stews, condemns Marriage, ſells Pardons, and Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizes Traitors. So that ſurely were there nothing but this, it were enough for ever to oblige our thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs.</p>
            <p>Yet beſides, (for ever to engage us to thy ſervice) how haſt thou choſen us out of all the Earth, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided us from the reſt of the World, that we might be a ſingular Pattern, and ſtrange wonder of thy bounty? How haſt thou fenced us about with the Hedg of good Diſcipline, of wholſom Laws, of gracious Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with the Brazen Wall of thy Almighty and mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous protection! never people had more exquiſite rules of juſtice; thou haſt not left us to the mercy of a rude Anarchy, or a Tyrannical violence, but haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated us by Laws of our own asking, and ſwayed us by the juſt Scepters of moderate Princes.</p>
            <p>How haſt thou made us members of a Church, as pure for Doctrine and Diſcipline, as any that either is,
<note place="margin">See Art. 6. of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> or has been theſe fifteen hundred years; a Church which has no other rule of Faith and Practice than the holy Scriptures. A Church that receives for Canonical, neither more nor leſs, than thoſe Books, of whoſe Authority there was never any doubt. A Church that profeſſes the ſame Faith and no more, than what all Chriſtians have made the Badge and Symbol of theirs; namely,
<note place="margin">Art. 8.</note> that which is briefly compiled in the Apoſtles Creed, explained in thoſe others, ſtiled the <hi>Nicene</hi> and <hi>Athanaſian.</hi> A Church where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are uſed the ſame Sacraments Chriſt left in his,
<note place="margin">Art. 25.</note> and no other. A Church, the Adminiſtration of whoſe Worſhip and Sacraments are in a Language underſtood by all thoſe that are concerned in them, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. and thoſe performed with ſuch Rites, as are conſonant to the Word of God, and the direction of the ſame Apoſtle, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40.) in decency and order. Laſtly, we are members of a Church, which
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:36564:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>above all other Conſtitutions in the Chriſtian World, enforces the great duty of obedience and ſubmiſſion <hi>to Kings, and all that are in authority under them,</hi> and this <hi>not only for wrath,</hi> but <hi>for Conſcience ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, O Lord! haſt thou courted us by thy favours, in the miraculous reſtoring, and gracious preſerving hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto the breath of our noſtrils, thine Anointed Servant, and under his protection the ſolemnities of thy Sacred Ordinances, the eſtabliſhment of our Laws, and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of our Intereſts. Thus hath the vigilant eye of thy Providence, out of the Window of Heaven watcht over this Nation for good: not an helliſh Pioneer could mine under ground, but thou haſt ſpied him out; nor a dark-Lanthorn offer to deceive midnight, but thou haſt deſcried it; not a Plot, not a purpoſe of evil could look out, but thou haſt diſcovered it, and glorified thy mercy in our deliverance.</p>
            <p>And now what ſervice. what obedience, what thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, muſt ſuch a Defender, ſuch a Protector, ſuch a deliverer expect, from a people ſo wonderfully obliged? But O my ſoul! what deplorable retributions have we made? When God gave us great and long proſperity, like <hi>Jeſhurun</hi> we waxed fat, and kicked againſt him. When he threw us into horrid confuſions, from which we ſaw little hope of ariſing, even in the time of that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, did we treſpaſs yet more againſt him. When by miracles of mercy he turned our Captivities, we ſoon returned to our wallowing in our former or greater fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs. Even while he has of late appeared for us, by diſcovering the Plots and Contrivances, of our implaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enemies of the Romiſh Faction, we have been in the mean time (and that moſt impudently) by our ſins fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt heaven, and againſt him.</p>
            <p>Vice formerly, like an old Curteſanguilty of her own witheredheſs, durſt not walk abroad without a borrowed
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:36564:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>Mask. They are frontleſs <hi>Zimries,</hi> that bring Whores to their Tents in the face of all <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Yet ſuch is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchedneſs of the Age wherein we live, that he is look'd upon as a cowardly ſinner, that is aſhamed to ſhew his face, though the ſpots of his guilt be written there; we even dare noon-day to witneſs our ungodlineſs, and do our villanies, as the Phariſees gave their Alms, <hi>to be ſeen of men.</hi> O the Oaths and blaſphemies that are to be heard in each Corner of our Streets! It is not only a faſhiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſin, and the Mode of the vain Gallants; but it is ſpread among the Herd; the brutiſh among the People are got to it; the very Vagabond, and he that has ſcarce a rag to his back, will ſwagger with his Oaths; O that that Name which is Reverend to Angels, and terrible to Devils; O that that Name we have been ſo oft delivered by from the hands of our Enemies, ſhould be ſo profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned! A complaint we have cauſe to ſill up with tears, more than words. Have we ſo learnt Chriſt, as only to ſwear by him? Will neither the mercies received, nor thoſe we expect, charm our lips from ſuch a Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion?</p>
            <p>What drinkings, what ſtaggerings, what reelings are to be ſeen in all parts of our Land? This deluge of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs has drown'd the face of the earth, and riſen many Cubits above the higheſt Mountains of Religion and good Laws. What extortings, what defraudings, what oppreſſings of the poor, what covetings, (even the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to a further Reformation, look aſquint with a Sacrilegious eye upon the ſmall remnant of the Churches Patrimony) what repinings, what traducings of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy, what Atheiſtical diſcourſings of a Deity? It is deplorable to ſee how theſe ſinners are ſet down in the ſeat of the Scorner; and ſince they cannot argue, reſolve to laugh all Piety out of countenance.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:36564:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Yet alas, were theſe the ſins of ignorance, of infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, they might be worthy of a pious pity. But O the high hand of our preſumptuous offences! we draw ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity with the ſtrings of vanity, and ſhoot up thoſe hateful ſhafts againſt heaven: Did we ſit in darkneſs and the ſhadow of death, as too many Pagan and Popiſh Regions do, theſe works of darkneſs would be leſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable: But now that the glorious Sun of the Goſpel has darted its Rays, has ſhined ſo long bright in our faces, nay, even now when God has declared viſibly for us; What can we plead againſt our own confuſion? O God! where ſhall we appear, when thy very favours aggravate our Crimes, and thy Judgments.</p>
            <p>What pious ſoul can conſider all this, and much more, and not fear that all theſe mercies are but fore-runners of ſome greater miſeries, that all our preſervations are but reſervations to ſome more ſignal deſtruction? How juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may heaven give us over into the hands of our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, depopulate our Cities, deſtroy our whole Nation like <hi>Sodom,</hi> and make us the ſcorn and Proverb of all ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Generations?
<note place="margin">Dan. 9.</note> But, O our God, let thine anger and fury be turned away from thy <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> thy holy Mountain. O Lord hear, O Lord forgive, O Lord har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and do: Defer not for thine own ſake, O our God, for thy City, and thy people that are called by thy Name.</p>
            <p>But what ſpeak I of not deferring to a God of mercy, who is more ready to give than we to crave, more loth to ſtrike than we to ſmart, and when he muſt Complains, <hi>Why will you die O houſe of Iſrael?</hi> To a God who in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite of all our ſins, of all our impieties, of all our ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, does ſtill continue his favours, does ſtill preſerve us from our Adverſaries that delight in bloud. Let me rather direct the diſcourſe to our ſelves, the fault is our own if we periſh; Heaven has not, nor will not be wanting, if we
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:36564:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>do but our parts. And therefore that Iniquity may never be our ruine, that God may never repent of his protecting and delivering of us, let us reſolve for the future to be in good earneſt Pious to our God, Loyal to our King, and Loving and Charitable one towards another.</p>
            <p>Let our Repentance be a real <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſting of our ſelves of all thoſe ſinful habits, with which we have provoked Heaven; let each man rend his heart, with ſorrow for his own ſins, and the ſins of his People; let every man ranſack his own ſoul, and life, and offer an holy violence to all thoſe ſinful Corruptions, that may hinder heavens protecting of us, and let not theſe reſolutions end with the day; let us not think it enough to forbear a meal, or to hang down our heads like a Bull-ruſh for a day, but let us break the bonds of wickedneſs, and in a true contrition of ſoul vow and perform better obedience.</p>
            <p>Let our Loyalty be ſuch as it ought, true and ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; let no murmurings, nor complainings find enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment in our breaſts. It is the trick of Mutineers, of impenitent Covenanters, to ſay, the former days were better than theſe: And if they once come to wear their teeth in their Tongues, as <hi>Shimei</hi> did, they will do what they can to have the Trumpet at their mouths, as <hi>Sheba</hi> had. Let not us that decry <hi>Romes</hi> Supremacy, make a Pope of an Anarchy. God himſelf ſays, <hi>By me Kings Reign,</hi> not by the Pope, nor by the People. In a word, let us not be leſs free in expoſing our Lives and Eſtates, for the preſervation of our King and Country, than our Adverſaries are to deſtroy both. It is a pity but his Neck ſhould hang in ſuſpence with his Conſcience in a halter, who ſcruples to venture all for his King, the Church, and his Country.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Let us learn to be unanimous, it is by our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union our Enemies are ſo ſtrong. Were we but ſo wiſe,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:36564:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>as to ſtand as a City that is compact together, and not fall out about Circumſtances, and Points of leſs moment, while we agree in the main ſubſtance; the Skirts of the Scarlet Whore had been rent to pieces ere this, and the Walls of <hi>Babylon</hi> with the Trumpet of the Goſpel would have long ſince fallen down, as <hi>Jericho</hi> at thoſe of the Sanctuary. To conclude, Let us keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace; and though we may differ in Opinions, let us not differ in our Affections, but unite againſt theſe common Enemies of our Intereſt, and make our hearty Prayers to God, that he may ſtill continue his mercies, infatuate and defeat the Counſels of theſe our bloudy and unparallel'd Adverſaries; continue the light of the Goſpel to us and our Poſterity; beſtow his abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant bleſſings upon his Sacred Majeſty, and this preſent Parliament; make us all happy here, and eternally happy hereafter. <hi>AMEN.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:36564:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books newly Printed for, and ſold by</hi> Thomas Fox, <hi>at the</hi> Angel <hi>in</hi> Weſtminſter Hall.</head>
            <list>
               <item>A Sermon preached at the Funeral of the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Paget,</hi> Baron of <hi>Beaude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert,</hi> &amp;c. by <hi>John Heynes</hi> M.A. and Preacher of the new Church <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> quarto ſtitch'd.</item>
               <item>A ſeaſonable advice to all true Proteſtants in <hi>England</hi> in this preſent poſture of affairs; diſcovering the preſent deſigns of the Papiſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by a ſincere lover of his King and Country. quarto ſtitch'd.</item>
               <item>Holy Rules and Helps to Devotion both in Prayer and Practice, in two parts. Written by the Right Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father in God <hi>Bryan Duppa,</hi> late Lord Biſhop of <hi>Winton,</hi> in the time of his Sequeſtration. Twelves, bound.</item>
               <item>The Legacy of the Right Reverend Father in God <hi>Herbert</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Hereford,</hi> or a ſhort determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all Controverſies we have with the Papiſts, by Gods holy Word. The ſecond Impreſſion Corrected, with additions by the Author. Quarto ſtirch'd.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Grand Cyrus</hi> compleat, a Romance. Folio.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clelia,</hi> a Romance. Folio.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Peter Heylins</hi> Geography. Folio.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Farindons</hi> Sermons in three Volumes. Folio.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pharamond,</hi> a Romance. Folio.</item>
               <item>Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> laſt Speech and thanks to her laſt Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, after her delivery from the Popiſh Plots, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:36564:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
